CURRICULUM VITAF

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Name Address

Telephone E-Mail Nationality Date of birth Family situation

▶ Summary





I am a **researcher** in the areas of Information Retrieval and Data Mining, currently working in Telefonica Research, Barcelona. My current research focus is on **Recommender Systems** and neighboring technologies such as **User Modeling** and **Social Networks**. I am interested in applied research as well as systems and software engineering and technical management. I have authored more than 50 publications and several patents.

Previously to my current position, my focus was on Multimedia and Immersive Systems and I worked as Research Director for CREATE (Center for Research in Electronic Art Technology) and Associate Director of the Media Arts and Technology Initiatives, both at the University of California Santa Barbara, where I directed the Allosphere project.

Apart from my research, I am interested on **research and technical management**, software development and **agile** methods. I am the main proponent of the Agile Research Manifesto.

After studying Telecommunications Engineering – roughly equivalent to ECE –, I obtained a PhD on Computer Science and Communications from the Universitat Pompeu Fabra (Barcelona, Spain).

As a **university professor** I have lectured on Software Engineering, Information Retrieval, Information Systems for managers, and different courses related to Multimedia and Audio.

I have experience in managing teams, especially using agile methods such as **eXtreme Programming** and **Scrum**. I am passionate about web and **digital culture** in general and a convinced advocate of **Open Source** methods and principles.

Main research areas

information retrieval, recommender systems, web science, social networks, user modeling, data mining, personalization, multimedia systems, audio and music processing

JOBS

Research and Research Management

- ▶ Period
- o Employer
- ⊳ 2007 until Now
- Position
- Main responsibilities

2007-

Telefonica Research

177, Via Augusta, Barcelona, 08021, Spain

Web Science, Recommender Systems, and User Modeling Research Scientist

Telefonica is one of the largest Telecommunications Company in the World. As a Research Scientist in Telefonica Research I have led the area of Web Science with a specific focus on Social Networks and Recommender Systems. During this time I have led postdoc researchers and interns from around the world. My main goal as a researcher was to obtain top-tier publications in the field (see Publication list below) and generate internal IP in the form of patents and tech transfer. I have also acted as a high-profile consultant to development teams dealing with projects in those same areas.

Furthermore, I have also become involved in many different *horizontal* activities in the company:

- Suggested and promoted the use of Agile Methodologies (such as eXtreme Programming and Scrum) in the company. As such I then became part of the Methodologies Committee.
- Founder member of the Software Architecture Special Interest Internal Group, where I acted as a consultant.
 Amog other activities, I was in charge of assessing the maturity level of software architects in Telefonica R&D.
- Member of the Education Committee, where strategies for internal courses were discussed
- Involved in many activities related to Innovation and Strategic Planning. For instance, I was part of the Telefonica Ambassadors For Innovation, a team of 400 people selected from the whole Telefonica Corporation to discuss and promote Innovation.
- Member of the Selection Committee for high-profile software engineers or architects. In my role I inteviewed candidates and also proposed a methodology for interviews.

- ▶ Period
- o Employer
- ⊳ 2006 until 2007
- Position
- Main responsibilities

- ▶ Period
- Employer
- > 2005 until 2007
- Position
- Main responsibilities
- ▶ Period
- Employer
- ▶ 1999 until 2005
- Position
- Main responsibilities

2006-2007

University of California Santa Barbara

The Allosphere Project

Associate Director for the Media Arts and Technology Initiatives Under direct supervision of the Director, responsible for industry relation, grant writing, facility coordination and PR for a \$40 million multimedia research center to be hosted in the California Nanosystems Institute. Direct supervision of technical issues related to one of the largest immersive environments in the world, an spherical building called the Allosphere http://www.allosphere.ucsb.edu.

2005-2007

University of California Santa Barbara

Center for Research in Electronic Arts and Technology

Research Director

Direct responsability over research coordination, planning and facility management for this research center that includes 3 different labs/studios and around 20 different researchers http://www.create.ucsb.edu.

1999-2005

Universitat Pompeu Fabra

Music Technology Group

Researcher/Project Manager

Working under direct supervision of the head of the group, Dr. Xavier Serra, I was responsible for teams of up to 8 researchers. I was one of the 5 members in the MTG Management Board. Project manager developer and designer of the CLAM framework for audio and music applications http://clam-project.org. Among others, I participated, always with managing responsabilities, in the following publicly founded projects: SIMAC http://www.semanticaudio.org, AGNU-LA http://www.agnula.org, CUIDADO, TABASCO. I also participated in different projects for companies such as Yamaha Japan.

Teaching

▶ Period

o Employer

⊳ 2010 until Now

Position

Main responsibilities

▶ Period

Employer

⊳ 2007 until 2010

Position

Main responsibilities

▶ Period

o Employer

▶ 1999 until 2005

o Position

Main responsibilities

2007-

EADA Business School, Barcelona (SPAIN)

Information Systems

Associate Professor

Associate professor teaching Information Systems and Technology to prospective managers and business leaders enrolled in full or part-time MBA's in one of the world's top 100 Business Schools.

2007-2010

Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Barcelona (SPAIN)

Software Engineering and Information Retrieval

Associate Professor

Associate professor and main coordinator of the undergraduate courses on Software Engineering and Information Retrieval. During this time I also directed several student Undergrad, Master and PhD Thesis.

1999-2005

Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Barcelona (SPAIN)

Software Engineering, Music and Audio Engineering, Program-

ming & Data Structures, Database Programming

Assistant Professor

Assistant Professor at the Computer Science Studies of the

Pompeu Fabra University (UPF). Teaching: "Software

Engineering" with a focus on Object Oriented Analysis/Design and C++, "Data Structures" and "Database Programming". Also responsible for Master Thesis / Visiting Students. During this

time I directed around 15 student Thesis.

Consulting and others

▶ Period

o Employer

> 2005 until 2008

Main responsibilities

2005-2008

The Sound Guy Inc., Audio Impressions, ...

Software Development

Development of severl digital audio applications such as a crossplatform Audio Processing software plugin based on spectral transformations.

EDUCATION

▶ Period

Acquired qualifications

o Institute

Principal subjects

Results

▶ Period

Acquired qualifications

University Results

▶ Period

Acquired qualifications

Results

▶ Period

Subject Summary 1999-2005

PhD on Computer Science and Digital Communications

Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF), Barcelona (SPAIN)

Software Engineering, Multimedia Systems

Under the supervision of Dr. Xavier Serra I read my dissertation entitled "An Object-Oriented Metamodel for Digital Signal Processing with a focus on Audio and Music" receiving the highest degree (Cum Laude).

1992-1999

Telecommunications Engineering (roughly equivalent to ECE, in-

cluding Master Degree)

Universitat Politecnica de Catalunya (UPC), Barcelona (SPAIN)

The Final Studies project on a language for describing musical scores and instruments and its corresponding implementation

received the highest degree (Cum Laude).

1988-1992

Secondary School

At the end of the studies received the highest degree (Honour

Mention) and an official honor grant to access university in Spain.

1984-1985

Primary School Abroad Studies

Studied sixth grade at the Twin Falls Elementary School, Twin

Falls, Idaho (USA).

SOFTWARE

Tasks

⊳ Period 2009–

o Name iPhone geo-personalized Recommendations

Summary
A mobile application that provides personalized and geolocated

movie recommendations that are playing near current location

Coordinator of the project.

⊳ Period 2009–

Name
Music Expert Recommendation

Summary
A cross-platform distributed application for recommending mu-

sic based on personal tastes and critic ratings. Developes in

Flex/AIR + Python

o Tasks Coordinator of the project.

⊳ Period 2002–

Name
CLAM (C++ Library for Audio and Music)

o Summary A Free framework for developing audio and music applica-

tions http://clam-project.org. It received the 2006 ACM Award to the Best Open Source Multimedia Software. Since 2007 it is part of the Google Summer of Code Program. It has

received grants from several public administrations.

Tasks
Coordinator of the project since its inception.

▶ Period 2005–2006

NameAnnotator

Summary
An application for automatic description extraction from audio

sources plus manual annotation and XML output (available as

Open Source software through the CLAM webpage).

Tasks
Main Developer and software designer

▶ Period 2005–2009

NameSpectral Machine

Summary
A crossplatform plugin (VST/AU, Win/OSX) for spectral audio

transformations developed for the Soundguy Inc. company.

Tasks
Developer and software designer

⊳ Period 2006

∘ Name Space

Summary
Software for spatializing musical instruments

Tasks
Developer and consultant for AudioImpressions

PUBLICATIONS

Selected Recent Publications

- → Amatriain, X. Pujol, J.M.Jaimes, A. Oliver, N. [2010]
- A. Karatzoglou, X.Amatriain, L. Baltrunas, N.Oliver [2010]
- ⊳ R. Garcia, X. Amatriain [2010]
- N. Lathia, S. Hailes, L. Capra, and X. Amatriain [2010]
- J. Ahn, X. Amatriain [2010]
- N. Tintarev, A. Flores, X. Amatriain [2010]
- ⊳ Amatriain, X. Arumi, P. [2010]
- ⊳ Amatriain, X. Lathia, N., Kwak, H. Oliver, N. [2009]
- ⊳ Amatriain, X. Pujol, J.M., Oliver, N. [2009]
- ▶ Lathia, N. Amatriain, X. Pujol, J.M. [2009]
- ⊳ Amatriain, X. Pujol, J.M. Tintarev, N. Oliver, N. [2009]
- ⊳ Amatriain, X. Baltrunas, L. [2009]

Data Mining Methods for Recommender Systems In Handbook of Recommender Systems. P. Kantor, F. Ricci, L. Rokach, B. Shapira (ed.). Springer. 2010

Multiverse Recommendation: N-dimensional Tensor Factorization for Context-aware Collaborative Filtering. in the **2010 ACM Recsys Conference**

Geolocated Movie Recommendations based on Expert Collaborative Filtering. in the 2010 ACM Recsys Conference

Hybrid Methods for Recommending Connections in Online Social Networks. in the Workshop on Recommender Systems and the Social Web in the **2010 ACM Recsys Conference**

Temporal Diversity in Recommender Systems. in the **2010 ACM SIGIR Conference**.

Towards Fully Distributed and Privacy-preserving Recommendations via Expert Collaborative Filtering and RESTful Linked Data. in ACM/IEE Conference on **Web Intelligence**

Off the beaten track - a mobile field study exploring the long tail of mobile tourist recommendations. in the 2010 Mobile HCI Conference

Frameworks Generate Domain-Specific Languages : A casestudy in the Multimedia Domain. In IEEE Transactions of Software Engineering

The Wisdom of the Few. A Collaborative Filtering Approach Based on Expert Opinions from the Web. **SIGIR'09**

I like it... I like it not: Measuring User Ratings Noise in Recommender Systems. UMAP 09 (User Modeling, Adaptation, and Personalization

Collaborative Filtering With Adaptive Information Sources. The 7th Workshop on Intelligent Techniques for Web Personalization & Recommender Systems Held in conjunction with IJCAI-09

Rate it Again: Increasing Recommendation Accuracy by User re-Rating. 2009 ACM RecSys Conference

Towards Time-Dependent Recommendation based on Implicit Feedback. Context-aware Recommender Systems Workshop in 2009 ACM RecSys Conference

→ Amatriain X., Kuchera-Morin J., Hollerer T., Pope S.T. [2009] The Allosphere: An Immersive Multimedia Instrument for Scientific Data Discovery and Artistic Exploration in IEEE Multimedia, 16 (2). April, 2009

Combining multi-level audio descriptors via web identification and aggregation, in World Wide Web Conference (WWW'09).

M. Cha, P. Rodriguez, J. Crowfort, S. Moon, X.Amatriain [2008]

Watching TV over an IP Network in Proceedings of the 8th ACM SIGCOMM conference on Internet measurement

▶ Amatriain, X. [2007]

A Domain-Specific Metamodel for Multimedia Processing Systems in **IEEE Transactions on Multimedia**. Volume 9 Issue 6. October 2007

▶ Amatriain, X. [2007]

CLAM, A Framework for Audio and Music Application Development in IEEE Software. January/February 2007. pp 82-85.

SELECTED RECENT PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

⊳ Period 2010

 Activity
Invited Talk at Free University of Bolzano to celebrate its 10th anniversary "The Beauty of Computing... with People"

⊳ Period 2010

o Activity General Conference co-Chair for 4th ACM Conference on Rec-

ommender Systems (Barcelona, Spain)

⊳ Period 2010

o Activity Invited talk to SIGIR 2010 Industry track Being Social: Research

in Context-aware and Personalized Information Access @ Tele-

fonica.

▶ Period 2008-2010

Activity
Senior Program Committee member for the ACM Recommender

Systems Conference (Recsys)

⊳ Period 2010

• Activity Program Committee member for the ACM SIGIR Conference

⊳ Period 2009

o Activity Invited Talk at Boston University "It's all about the Data. Data-

driven approaches to the Recommender Problem"

⊳ Period 2008

Activity | Invited talk in the "Future of Web Search Workshop" organized

by Yahoo!

RECOMMENDATIONS

*

Public recommendations issued current by and former colleagues in LinkedIn can be retrieved the corresponding LinkedIn page (http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=7453935#recommendations). More formal and individualized recommendations may be available upon request.

ABILITIES

COMPUTER SKILLS

- Math/Stats/Machine Learning tools: R, SPSS, Matlab, Octave, Weka, Orange, Torch, libsvm, gnuplot, matplotlib...
- Programming Languages: Proficient C++ programmer, C, Java, Python, Ruby, Java-script, Matlab, HTML, XML, LaTeX...
- Development environments: GNU, Eclipse, XCode, Visual Studio, KDevelop
- Frameworks and API's: Hadoop, Qt, OpenGL, Weka, Flkt, Carbon...
- Development tools: unit testing tools (such as XUnit), profilers (Valgrind, Shark, Rational Distiller,), UML modelers (Rational Rose, Umbrello...), CVS, svn, ...
- Methodologies: eXtreme Programming, Scrum, testdriven development, RUP...
- Operating Systems: GNU/Linux, OSX, Microsoft Windows

LINKS

- Webpage: http://xavier.amatriain.net
- Blog: http://technocalifornia.blogspot.com
- Twitter: http://www.twitter.com/xamat
- LinkedIn: http://www.linkedin.com/in/xamatriain
- Slideshare: http://www.slideshare.net/xamat

Barcelona, January 2010 Xavier Amatriain